Guide to the Michael J. Ellis papers, 1975-1993
Ellis, Michael J. papers, 1975-1993
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Michael J. Ellis papers, 1975-1993
7615
Michael J. Ellis
5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, subject files, audiocassettes, manuscript, book.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, subject files, audiocassettes, and other materials documenting the shift from gay liberation to gay and lesbian activism, and concerning the establishment of organizations, programs, and issues at Cornell and in Ithaca, including the Cornell University Library's Human Sexuality Collection, Ithaca's Fair Practice Ordinance, the adoption of Local Law C, the addition of sexual orientation to the University's Equal Opportunity statement, and the development of AIDS awareness and policy.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Resident Director, Ecology House; Director of Robert Purcell Union; Associate Dean and Director of Willard Straight Hall, Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, subject files, audiocassettes, and other materials documenting the shift from gay liberation to gay and lesbian activism, and concerning the establishment of organizations, programs, and issues at Cornell and in Ithaca, including the Cornell University Library's Human Sexuality Collection, Ithaca's Fair Practice Ordinance, the adoption of Local Law C, the addition of sexual orientation to the University's Equal Opportunity statement, and the development of AIDS awareness and policy.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ellis, Michael J.; Cornell University--Students.
Subjects:
Gay liberation movement--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Gays--Laws and legislation.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Lesbian and Gay Rights
Box 1
A. General Correspondence
B. Cornell
Correspondence
Events and issues
Organizations
C. Ithaca
D. National
Series II. AIDS
Box 2
A. Cornell
Events, organizations, and issues
B. Ithaca
Series III. Tapes
Box 2
Series IV. Conferences/Workshops
Boxes 2-3
A. Ithaca
B. National
Series V. Professional Writing
Box 3
A. Journal Manuscript
B. Book
Series VI. Subject Files
Box 3
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Lesbian and Gay Rights
  - General Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1977-1981, Highlights: 1977 letters to President and first Lady Carter, and reply from Margaret Midge Costanza, Assistant to the President 1977 letter to Supreme Court 1978 letter to Jerry Falwell other letter to Catholic and other religious leaders over the years, written as a Christian concerned about gay rights 1979 letter to Ann Landers 1979 letter from U.S. Rep. Matt McHugh on abortion rights 1980 letter from INS re: "homosexual aliens" 1981 letters to and from Dianne Feinstein, Mayor of San Francisco 1981 letters to and from Senator Patrick Moynihan about Family Protection Act correspondence with Cornell chapter of Phi Kappa Psi fraternity (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1995, Highlights: 1985 letter to Morley Safer, "60 Minutes" 1986 letter to Dan Rather, CBS News 1988 letter to Ithaca Times, and State Sen. James Seward 1995 letters to and from Fairfax County School Board, Virginia (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cornell
    - Cornell related notes and correspondence, 1982-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Cornell Sex Education Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bruce Voeller, Brian McKnaught, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Charles Bryden, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - March on Washington, 1979, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Cornell Gay Scholarship Offer, Cornell Libraries, 1981-1982, 1982-1992, Includes handwritten note from Barbara Gittings, then coordinator of the Gay Task Force of the American Library Association: "Thanks for sending stuff on the fascinating story of the gay scholarship and the gay books fund! Do please let me know the final outcome. - Barbara Also, 1982 letter from Michael Ellis sent to 14 faculty and staff members, including University Librarian Louis Martin, along with American Library Association's Gay Bibliography (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Homosexuality and Social Justice," Archdiocese of San Francisco, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sexual Preference Resolution, Sept. 21 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ROTC/Military Gay Issues, 1983-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Ithaca Journal on Homosexuality, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Ed McKeown re: discrimination at Cornell, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual Awareness Month (April), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Homophobia Training, March 14, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cornell Gay Student Groups, 1979-1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - CUGALA (Cornell University Gay and Lesbian Association) correspondence, 1980-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Lesbian and Gay Faculty and Staff at Cornell, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Adding Sexual Orientation to Equal Educational and Employment Opportunity Statement, May, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ithaca
    - "Media," mostly Ithaca and Cornell clippings, 1983-1993 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Deb Price editorials, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Gay rights, Ithaca, 1982-1990 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Ithaca correspondence, 1984-1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Outlines articles by Ellis, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Articles, clippings and flyers, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - "Male Issues", 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Tompkins County Fair Practice Ordinance, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Domestic Partnership, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Bias Related Violence, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - National
    - Gay Politics correspondence, 1982-1992 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Supreme Court Decisions, 1986, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence with Human Rights Campaign Fund re: job, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - GLAAD (Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - New York State Lesbian/Gay Lobby/How to Lobby, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - ACU-I International Conference, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - NGLTF Campus Project (National Gay and Lesbian Task Force), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Outright Speakers and Talent Bureau, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Senior Action in a Gay Environment, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - PFLAG (Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays), 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Series II. AIDS
  - Cornell
    - AIDS related material-Cornell, 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Project Coordinator, AIDS Risk Reduction, Cornell, ca. 1987-989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cornell University AIDS Advisory Committee, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Cornell University AIDS Advisory Committee, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Cornell University AIDS Advisory Committee, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cornell University AIDS Advisory Committee, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Gay/Lesbian/Bisexual Mental Health Conference, Cornell University, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Cornell University AIDS Packet", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Cornell Panel Discussion on AIDS: Connecting Science and Public Policy, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "AIDS: A Resource for the Cornell Community," Amy Amelkin, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ithaca
    - AIDS Conference, 1985, Planned Parenthood of Tompkins County, Tompkins County Community College, Hospicare (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - AIDS-related material-Ithaca area, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Tompkins County AIDS Task Force, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Tompkins County AIDS Task Force, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - AIDS Update, May 1987, Planned Parenthood of Tompkins County, Tompkins County Community College, et al. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "AIDS and Religion Resource Directory", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - AIDS Pamphlets and Reports, ca. 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - AIDS Teleconference, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Tompkins County Mental Health Association (TCMHA) Homophobia Training/Education, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - AIDSWork of Tompkins County Benefit, April 20, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous AIDS information, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - AIDS-related clipping, articles, 1983-1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - AIDS-related material--national, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - HIV Treatment Information, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Series III. Tapes
  - Sage Chapel Services, March 8, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Developing an AIDS Policy, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - AIDS and the College Student, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Supervising Gay and Lesbian Employees, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Working with Gay Students and Staff: Legal, Political, and Practical Insight, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Series IV. Conferences/Workshops
  - Ithaca
    - Ithaca Men's Network--Men's Fest, Ken George Workshop, October 18-20, 1985. Also miscellaneous materials re: Ithaca Men's Network, c.1990 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Teenage Sexuality-Planned Parenthood Conference, October 24, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Countering Homophobia-Planned Parenthood Conference, October 4, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Homophobia Workshop-Planned Parenthood, June 12, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Planned Parenthood Workshops, 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
  - National
    - University Workshop on Homophobia, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - AASECT Conference (American Association of Sex Educators, Counselors, and Therapists), June 6-10, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - AASECT Conference (American Association of Sex Educators, Counselors, and Therapists), June 6-10, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - HRT Gay and Lesbian Awareness Training (Human Relations Training), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Campaign to End Homophobia [Conference on Homophobia Education], May 20-22, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
- Series V. Professional Writing
  - Journal Manuscript (includes relevant correspondence), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Contribution to book, Controversies in Family Studies, by Margaret and Harold Feldman (1984), (includes relevant correspondence, 1984-1986) (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series VI. Subject Files
  - AIDS Training Outline, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - ASC (Alternative Spirituality Community), 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Homophobia Training Material, ca. 1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Periodicals Separated from #7615:
Brother: Mar. 1988
Choice: Spring, Winter 1986; Spring-Winter 1987; Spring 1988; Spring, Fall-Winter 1989; Spring, Fall 1990; Winter 1991
Empathy: Fall-Winter 1988; Fall-Winter, Spring-Summer 1989/1990
EMV Newsletter (Ending Men's Violence): Jan. 1989
Equity Institute News: Winter 1989
IMN Newsletter (Ithaca Men's Network): Aug., Oct. 1985; Aug., Nov. 1989
Journal of Sex Education and Therapy: Fall/Winter 1981
Men's Studies Newsletter: Aug./Sept. 1986
Men's Work: Dec./Jan. 1986/1987; Jan. update, Mar./Apr., Jun. 1987
Out on Campus: Oct. 1989; Feb.-Mar. 1990
Resources, Research and Reviews: Mar. 1986; Jun., Oct. 1987; Feb., Apr., June, Sept. 1988; Feb. 1989; Feb., Apr. 1990
The Advocate: no. 426 (Aug. 6, 1985); no. 481 (Sept. 15 1987); no. 485 (Nov. 10, 1987); no. 511 (Nov. 8, 1988)
GLAAD Bulletin: Jan./Feb., Oct./Nov. 1989; Mar./Apr.-Sep./Oct. 1990; Jan./Feb. 1991; Pride Special and Jul./Aug. 1991-Nov./Dec. 1991; Mar./Apr.-May/Jun. 1992; Sep./Oct.-Nov./Dec. 1992
GLAAD Newsletter: Winter/Spring 1989
Images: no. 1 (Fall 1992)
Lambda Update: v. 8, nos. 1-2 (Spring, Fall 1991)
News from GAYPAC/GAYPAC News: Dec. 1979; Feb., Apr. 1980; Oct.-Dec. 1983; Feb.-Mar. 1984
Outlines: Dec. 1984; Feb. 1985 (2 different issues); Apr. 1985; Jun. 1985; Apr. 1986; Nov./Dec. 1986; Apr./May 1987; Summer 1987; Dec. 1987/Jan. 1988; Apr./May 1989; Sep. 1989; Sep./Oct. 1990; June 1992
Washington Blade: v. 18, no. 42 (Oct. 16, 1987)
AIDS Surveillance Monthly Update: Center for Disease Control, 1990
Monographs Separated from #7615:
Blank, Joani, The Playbook for Men about Sex San Francisco, Down There Press, 1975
HIV/AIDS: U.S. AIDS cases reported through January 1991 U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 1991
Making Colleges and Universities Safe for Gay and Lesbian Students: Report and Recommendations of the Governor's Commission on Gay and Lesbian Youth Boston, 1993